<div><font color="#444444">
<p align="justify" class="margined">
<span class="firstcharacter">H</span>ello. I'm Nishanth Prakash. I am currently a Visiting Researcher at the Hasso Plattner Institute, Potsdam, Germany. I graduated from National Institute of Technology Karnataka, Surathkal (NITK/KREC), with a BTech. degree in Computer Engineering in 2013. I then worked as a Software Developer at Netapp and then as a Research and Development Engineer at Aspiring Minds, about one year at each. 
<br/> <br/> 
My core research focus is in the deconstruction of human intelligence and cognition into mathematical constructs. I believe that this not only enables the understanding of the biological process of learning but also reciprocally help build biologically inspired artificial intelligent agents that can augment human abilities, overcome disabilities, improve human learning and cognition (resulting in effective education) and assist in the everlasting human enterprise of understanding the world.<br/><br/>

I believe that we can model human cognition by mining responses to well designed assessment-tests, analogous to the way dynamic testing procedures are used in understanding the behaviours of complex computer programs. By localizing a learners cognition on the spectrum of human cognitive spaces, we will then be able to provide personalized tutoring conducive for effective education. The emerging educational technologies such as Intelligent tutoring systems (ITSes), massive open online courses (MOOCs), and websites like Khan Academy and Codecademy enable us to do this with the enormous amount of educational data they collect. <i><b>My current research focus is in designing novel intelligent tutoring systems that evaluate computer programming ability and provide feedback for improving the same.</b></i> Over the last few years, I have developed a passion for Program Analysis and Machine Learning and would love to explore other interesting areas in the intersection of these field, such as Computer-Aided Program Synthesis and Software Engineering.<br/> <br/>

Check out the projects I have worked on related to this <a style="all:unset; color:#0000FF;" onmouseover="this.style.textDecoration='underline'; this.style.color='red';" onmouseout="this.style.textDecoration='none'; this.style.color='blue';" href="javascript:makeGetRequest('tv')">here</a>, <a style="all:unset; color:#0000FF;" onmouseover="this.style.textDecoration='underline'; this.style.color='red';" onmouseout="this.style.textDecoration='none'; this.style.color='blue';" href="javascript:makeGetRequest('sg')">here</a> and <a style="all:unset; color:#0000FF;" onmouseover="this.style.textDecoration='underline'; this.style.color='red';" onmouseout="this.style.textDecoration='none'; this.style.color='blue';" href="javascript:makeGetRequest('it')">here</a>. I have also been interested in the assessments of responses to other open response type questions: <a style="all:unset; color:#0000FF;" onmouseover="this.style.textDecoration='underline'; this.style.color='red';" onmouseout="this.style.textDecoration='none'; this.style.color='blue';" href="javascript:makeGetRequest('am')">here</a> is an ITS project I have worked on involving assessment of grammaticality in formal written discourse in the English language. <a style="all:unset; color:#0000FF;" onmouseover="this.style.textDecoration='underline'; this.style.color='red';" onmouseout="this.style.textDecoration='none'; this.style.color='blue';" href="javascript:makeGetRequest('fr')">Here</a> is one more ITS project I have worked on in the field of Physical Education.<br/> <br/>

You can find my other interests and activities <a style="all:unset; color:#0000FF;" onmouseover="this.style.textDecoration='underline'; this.style.color='red';" onmouseout="this.style.textDecoration='none'; this.style.color='blue';" href="javascript:makeGetRequest('in')">here</a> 
</p>
</font>
</div>
