

<div><font color="#444444">
<h2 class="margined">Realtime Gesture Recognition using Microsoft Kinect</h2>
<p align="justify" class="margined">
This project was part of what I worked on during the summer research internship at India Innovation Labs (May-July, 2011). As part of this project I developed a Realtime Gesture Recognition system for interaction with the humanoid robot PRATHAM (Personal Robot and Telepresence Humanoid with Autonomous Mobility) under the guidance of Dr. Ramachandra Budihal.<br/>
<br/>
Microsoft Kinect is used for the visual input and using OpenNI and NITE libraries the positions of certain parts of the body are tracked. The gestures are tracked and recognized using an Artificial Neural Networks architecture using back propagation algorithm, implemented using the Fast Artificial Neural Network (FANN) library. This system was implemented as a software stack on the Robot Operating System (ROS) in PRATHAM.<br/> 
<br/>
The system was able to recognize more than 20 gestures it was trained with accurately -- gestures done with either one or both of users arms. The system can easily be scaled to activity recognition systems by just tracking other parts of the body (due to the ease with which we can do this using the ROS-OpenNI stack). The code for this project can be found <a style="all:unset; color:#0000FF;" onmouseover="this.style.textDecoration='underline'; this.style.color='red';" onmouseout="this.style.textDecoration='none'; this.style.color='blue';" href="https://github.com/nishanthprakash/GestureRecognition_Kinect-ROS.git" target="_blank">here.</a><br/><br/><i>Some screenshots:</i><br> 
Shown in this screenshot is the user tracker which colors the users detected. In another window seen is the rx-graph generated which displays a visualization of a ROS Computation Graph, i.e. the ROS nodes (processes) that are currently running, as well as the ROS topics (named buses over which nodes exchange messages) that connect them. <br><br><img src="./nishanthprakash_files/gr1.jpg" width="495" height="330" style="margin:auto;display:block;"><br><br> Shown here is another screenshot showing the user tracker viewer.<br><br>
<img src="./nishanthprakash_files/gr2.jpg" width="495" height="330" style="margin:auto;display:block;">
</p>
</font>
</div>


