<div><font color="#444444">
<h2 class="margined">Test-Case Analytics</h2>
<p align="justify" class="margined">
Test cases are one way of estimating how correct a given program is. In general, more the testcases, the better we can estimate the semantics of the program. In the context of assessing thousands of programs solving the same problem, multiple test cases help us understand how and in what respects these programs differ. Designing good test cases that has high coverage across all these programs is in itself an interesting problem.<br/>
<br/>
On the flip side, we could also use programs as test cases to estimate how good our test suites are, and understand similarities and differences in the behavior of these test cases across the programs. We could gain interesting insights about redundencies in the test cases, understand whether we could discover salient concepts needed to solve a particular programming problem, and as to which test cases are corner cases (and tougher to meet), and also find anomalies in the problem description and/or the test cases designed for a programming problem.<br/> 
<br/>
I built a tool that generates statistics and visualizations to gain such insights on the then available data, over 2500 test cases spread across 50 programming problems attempted nearly by 18,000 candidates.<br/>
<br/>
The following is a screen shot of the part of the tool that deals with identifying anomalous behavior of test-cases.<br/><br/>
<center><img src="./nishanthprakash_files/tc_anoms.png" width="75%" style="margin:auto;display:inline-block;"></center><br/>
<br/>
</p>
<p align="justify" class="margined">
The following is a dendrogram visualization of hierarchical clustering of testcases (based on pass/fail across programs). The dendrogram below helped us identify clusters in testcases as shown below, resulting from two important concepts in the problem. (We later found that one of the concepts was not something we intended to test, adding an uncalled for impurity to the assessment objective; more on this in the blog post I've linked below<sup>[1]</sup>)<br/>
<br/>
<center><img src="./nishanthprakash_files/tc_dendrogram.png" width="45%" style="margin:auto;display:inline-block;"></center><br/>
<br/>
</p>
<p align="justify" class="margined">
The following is a histogram of candidate scores (test-cases based) for a particular problem, useful in understanding how difficult the programming problem is and if there are clusters in these scores. We would ideally want to design problems and their test-cases such that the scores are uniformly distributed across the whole range.<br/>
<br/><center><img src="./nishanthprakash_files/tc_hist.png" width="45%" style="margin:auto;display:inline-block;"></center>
</p>
<footer><hr>
<p align="justify" class="margined">
[1] A blog titled <a style="all:unset; color:#0000FF;" target="_blank" href="http://research.aspiringminds.com/test-case-analytics/" ><i><b>What we learn from patterns in test case statistics of student-written computer programs</b></i></a>, discusses some observations using this tool.
</p>
</footer>
</font>
</div>